<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christmas, the Christians grand feast: its original, growth, and observation, also of Easter, Whitsontide, and other holydayes modestly discussed and determined. Also the beginning of the yeare, and other things observable. Where also among other learned men, you have the judgment of those eminent men; Josephus Scaliger, Rodulphus Hospinian, Matthæus Beroaldus, Joh. Causabon, Doct. Fulk, M. Cartwright, Alsted, Hugh Broughton, Master Mead. / By Thomas Mocket; sometimes of Queens Colledge in Cambridge, and Mr. of Arts in both the Universities; and now pastor of Gildeston in Hartfordshire. Novemb. 26, 1650. Imprimatur, Edm. Calamy.</title>
            <author>Mocket, Thomas, 1602-1670?.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89194</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2304</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E619_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202886</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863025</idno>
            <idno type="RLIN">99863025</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115207</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89194)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115207)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 95:E619[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christmas, the Christians grand feast: its original, growth, and observation, also of Easter, Whitsontide, and other holydayes modestly discussed and determined. Also the beginning of the yeare, and other things observable. Where also among other learned men, you have the judgment of those eminent men; Josephus Scaliger, Rodulphus Hospinian, Matthæus Beroaldus, Joh. Causabon, Doct. Fulk, M. Cartwright, Alsted, Hugh Broughton, Master Mead. / By Thomas Mocket; sometimes of Queens Colledge in Cambridge, and Mr. of Arts in both the Universities; and now pastor of Gildeston in Hartfordshire. Novemb. 26, 1650. Imprimatur, Edm. Calamy.</title>
                  <author>Mocket, Thomas, 1602-1670?.</author>
                  <author>Scaliger, Joseph Juste, 1540-1609.</author>
                  <author>Hospinian, Rudolf, 1547-1626.</author>
                  <author>Beroald, Matthieu, d. 1576.</author>
                  <author>Fulke, William, 1538-1589.</author>
                  <author>Alsted, Johann Heinrich, 1588-1638.</author>
                  <author>Broughton, Hugh, 1549-1612.</author>
                  <author>Cartwright, Thomas, 1535-1603.</author>
                  <author>Mede, Joseph, 1586-1638.</author>
                  <author>Casaubon, Isaac, 1559-1614.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 25, [1] p. ;   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Wodenoth at the Star under Peters Church in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Dec. 6 1650", the 51 in imprint date crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Holidays --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fasts and feasts --  Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115207:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CHRISTMAS,
The <hi>Chriſtians</hi> grand Feaſt: Its <hi>Original, Growth,</hi> and <hi>Obſervation,
Alſo of</hi> Eaſter, Whitſontide, <hi>and</hi>
other Holydayes modeſtly diſcuſſed
and determined. Alſo the beginning of the Yeare,
<hi>and other things obſervable.</hi> Where alſo among other learned Men,
<hi>you have the judgment of thoſe eminent Men;</hi>
Joſephus Scaliger, Rodulphus Hoſpinian,
Matthaeus Beroaldus, Joh. Cauſabon,
<hi>Doct.</hi> Fulk, <hi>M.</hi> Cartwright,
Alſted, Hugh Broughton,
<hi>Maſter</hi> Mead.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <bibl>Epictetus.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>By THOMAS MOCKET;
Sometimes of Queens Colledge in <hi>Cambridge,</hi>
and Mr. of Arts in both the Univerſities;
and now Paſtor of <hi>Gildeſton</hi> in
<hi>Hartfordſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <p>Imprimatur,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>Novemb. 26, 1650.</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>Edm. Calamy.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Wodenoth</hi> at the Star under
<hi>Peters</hi> Church in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1651.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:115207:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115207:2"/>
            <head>CHRISTMAS,
The Chriſtians grand Feaſt: Its originall, growth &amp; obſervation;
diſcuſſed and determined.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the diſſolving of this doubt,<note place="margin">Saturnus Aegy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptius <hi>was wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> Cham, <hi>ſaith</hi> Laurentius Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domannus in Anno M. 1905, Saturnus Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonicus <hi>was cruell</hi> Nimrod, ibid.</note> and ſetling
all religious, and peaceable mens minds
and conſciences concerning the obſervation
of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Nativity, we muſt know</p>
            <p>1 That <hi>Saturn,</hi> who (as Heathens them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
inform us<note n="*" place="margin">Phornutus, <hi>Alſo</hi> Cicero de natura Deorum Macrobius Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnalium, l. 1. c. 7. Boccaçe <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nealogie of the gods,</hi>
               </note>) was ſon to <hi>Coelum,</hi> or
<hi>Coelus</hi> and <hi>Veſta,</hi> Father of the Heathen gods, took to
wife his own ſiſter <hi>Ops,</hi> by whom he had many children;
<hi>Jupiter, Juno, Neptune, Pluto,</hi> and others, <hi>Patri Coelo viri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia
exſecuit,</hi> he cut off his father <hi>Coelums genitalia,</hi> and
threw them into the Sea, a moſt unſon-like, and an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable
fact, he was famous in his generation, becauſe
he<note n="a" place="margin">Macrob. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnal. l. 1. c. 7. Polyd. Virgil. de invent<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ribus r<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rum, l. 3. c. 3.</note> firſt found out the art of grafting fruit trees and huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry
in <hi>Latium,</hi> a part of <hi>Italy,</hi> and taught it firſt in
<hi>Europe,</hi> he was generally honoured by the Heathens, as a
god, and to that end, ſacred rites were done unto him,
and the 25 of <hi>December,</hi> with the reſt of the days follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
ſeven days together, were appointed and generally
obſerved by the idolatrous Heathen, to that end, ſacrifices,
ſports, and other ſolemnities, were magnificently, and
with great preparation and rejoycing performed,<note n="b" place="margin">Polydor. Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gil. de invent. rerum, l. 2. c. 14 23. &amp; l. 5. c, 2. S<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neca Epiſt. 18 Prin Hiſtrom. p. 751. &amp;c.</note> which
the Apoſtle tels us is foul idolatry, <hi>a ſacrificing unto Devils,</hi>
1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 20. At which time alſo, there was a ſheaf of
Corn, offered to <hi>Ceres,</hi> their <hi>Goddeſſe of Corn,</hi> and an hymn
ſung in her praiſe, called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Alſo Feaſting,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115207:3"/>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Pol. Virg. de invent. l. 5. c. 2. Horatius Ca<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. l. 1. Ode 37. &amp; Sermo l. 2. Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyr. 7. <hi>Alſo</hi> Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gil. Ovid, &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lii.</note> Drinking, Stage-plays, Enterludes, Masks Mummeries,
Dancing, and all licentious diſſoluteneſſe by their <hi>Lords of
miſ-rule,</hi> (eſpecially in <hi>England,</hi> ſaith <hi>Polydore Virgil</hi>) who,
for that time commanded all in the houſe, the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,
as well as others. He was made propitious by ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
of men unto him, as they thought.<note n="d" place="margin">Plut. Moral. p 379.</note> His better part as
they believed) being tranſlated unto heaven, ſhineth forth
in the greateſt and higheſt of the ſeven Planets, called <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn,</hi>
a malevolent ſtar,<note n="e" place="margin">Stella nocens Saturnus. Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can.</note> Him, and alſo <hi>Belus, Jupiter, Mars,
Mercurius, Venus, Pluto, Neptune, Apollo, Bacchus, Flora,</hi>
and many other ſouls of great men departed, the <hi>Pagans</hi>
worſhipped for their gods, becauſe while on earth, they
deſerved well of mortall men, did many good things, ſaith
<hi>Lactantius Firminianus,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Lactantius in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitut. divin. l. 1.</note> who as <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Aug. de Civit. Dei, l. 3. c. 3. &amp; 17.</note> ſaith, were
known to have been adulterers, and notorious malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors,
though in ſome other things famous.<note place="margin">Sir <hi>W. Raleighs</hi> Hiſtory of the World <hi>p.</hi> 73. 75.</note>
            </p>
            <p>That feſtivall time in <hi>December,</hi> called <hi>Saturnalia, (Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns</hi>
feaſts, becauſe in honour of <hi>Saturn</hi> their idol god)
was called alſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Yule,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Athen. l. 14. Veteres Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi</hi> begin their year as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>à Domini praeſentiâ,</hi> which ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to his birth, ſome to his ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſme, &amp; ſome to the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Star to the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, <hi>Beroald. Chron. l. 4. c.</hi> 1.</note> becauſe of the ſheaf
then offer'd to <hi>Ceres,</hi> and hymn ſung in honour of her,
for the words were generally uſed both for a ſheaf and
that hymn, which time they ſpent in idolatrous ſacrificing,
feaſting, revelling, and the like, as above-ſaid.</p>
            <p>At this time was conſecrated to the honour of <hi>Saturn,
Ceres,</hi> and their goddeſſe <hi>Veſta,</hi> by the ancient Heathens
eſpecially.</p>
            <p>So <hi>the firſt day of January,</hi> commonly called <hi>New-years-day,</hi>
of which I have not yet obſerved any good reaſon in
Antiquity, ſave only this, becauſe the Chriſtians retained
the <hi>Julian</hi> Account and year, as the trueſt which begins
the year on the <hi>Kalends,</hi> or firſt day of <hi>January,</hi> as<note n="*" place="margin">Hoſpin. de o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rig<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne Feſt. Ch<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſtian. f. 31.</note> 
               <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpinian</hi>
obſerveth, without having reſpect to the true ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>connt
of the beginning of time, but conceive rather that
the year ſhould begin on <hi>March</hi> 25, when our Politicall
and Civil year begins, and the firſt day of the worlds crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
as ſome learned men think: Or rather now about the
tenth of <hi>March,</hi> when the Sun firſt enters into the firſt
degree of <hi>Aries,</hi> and begins our <hi>Spring,</hi> or about the 3<hi rend="sup">d.</hi> of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115207:3"/>
               <hi>Aprill,</hi> about which time <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſuffer'd, it being uſuall
with <hi>Antiquity,</hi> to record the day of the death of eminent
perſons in honour of them, for their birth day, becauſe
they then begin to live the life of Eternity. The <hi>Ancient
Heathens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>i</hi> Martis erat primus menſis, Veneriſque ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundus, Ovid. Faſt. lib. 1.</note> as the <hi>Romans,</hi> did begin their year with <hi>March,</hi>
as appears by the names of the Moneths ſtill in uſe among
us, namely, <hi>September, October, November, December,</hi> that
is the ſeventh, the eighth, ninth, and tenth moneth, till
<hi>Numa Pompilius</hi> the great forger and advancer of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the
Romane Idolatry and Superſtition, who began to
reign about the third year of the ſixteenth <hi>Olympiade,</hi> ſaith
<hi>Plutarch.</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Plut. in vita Numae Pompilii p. 48 Pol. Virg. de invent rerum l. 2. c. 4.</note> The <hi>Arabians</hi> and the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> began their
year with the Vernall Equinoctiall or Spring, and the
<hi>Jews,</hi> their Eccleſiaſticall year for holy feaſts and Church-affairs
with <hi>Abib</hi> about the latter end of our <hi>March. Or
elſe,</hi> we ſhould begin in <hi>September,</hi> as the <hi>Aſians,</hi> the later
and Chriſtian <hi>Greeks:</hi> for the <hi>Ancient Greeks</hi> began their
year with the <hi>Summers Solſtice,</hi> that is in <hi>June,</hi> as they did
alſo their <hi>Olympiades,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sc<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arpi Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon. p. 141. Laurent. Codo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannus Anna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. Beroaldus Chron. l. 4 c. 1. p. 236.</note> ſaith <hi>Beroaldus, The Eccleſiaſticall
Aſtrologers</hi> begin their year and account with <hi>September,</hi>
do alſo the <hi>Jews:</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> for legall, politicall, and civill
affairs, becauſe they generally believed the <hi>World</hi> was
then created, the fruits being then all ripe, and not any in
<hi>March</hi> at the Paſſeoeer, for then corn was green, and
green ears were offered to God, as appears by <hi>Exod.</hi> 9. 31.
32.<note place="margin">Avenarius in Lexico Hebr.</note> the word <hi>Abib,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies <hi>Spica cum culmo, ſpica
virens matureſcens,</hi> a green ear, earing, earing time <hi>Pagnin</hi>
and <hi>Avenarius,</hi> ſee <hi>Exod. 9. 31, 32. Levit.</hi> 2. 14. The <hi>Septu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agint</hi>
uſually renders it by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> new fruits: And the text
ſays expreſly that the plague of hail, <hi>Exod.</hi> 9. which we
may ſuppoſe hapned about the beginning of <hi>Abib, March</hi>
Moon, or a few days before (as Mr. <hi>Mead</hi> well conjectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth)
<hi>had ſmitten the flax and the barly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mead Diatriba 3. part. p. 627.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe the barly was
eared, and the flax bolled, but the wheat and the rye were not
eared,</hi> after which earing, it muſt have ſome time to ripen,
with us they have about two moneths and ſometimes
more, and ſo with them, (as I conceive) harveſt began
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115207:4"/>
(their two loaves of firſt fruits, and harveſt feaſt of them,
becauſe of the ripe corn) at <hi>Pentecoſt, Exod.</hi> 23. 16. the
beginning of harveſt and not the end, as ſome affirm, for
their ſeed time both for wheat and barly in <hi>Egypt</hi> (and
therefore alſo about that in <hi>Paleſtine</hi>) was in <hi>November,</hi>
and their barly was ripe in the ſixt moneth, but their wheat
not till the ſeventh, about a moneth after, as <hi>Pliny</hi> informs
us, which muſt be in <hi>May</hi> and <hi>June,</hi> the uſuall time of
<hi>Pentecoſt</hi> which fell out moſt commonly in <hi>May,</hi> therefore
this moneth was called <hi>Aethanim,</hi> which ſignifieth
<hi>ſtrengths,</hi> becauſe all things were created in the ſtrength,
and much about the time, our Bleſſed Saviour was born,
that moneth beginneth towards the end of our <hi>September</hi>
Moneth, but I return, having thought good to add a word
or two concerning the beginning of the year.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The firſt of January,</hi> commonly called <hi>New-years-day,</hi>
a part of our Chriſtmas was dedicated to the honour of
their <hi>two faced</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Polyd. Virgil. de invent. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, l. 2. c. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Idoll Janus</hi> ſo called, and pictured, bcauſe
he was a wiſe Prince, that did look back, and well obſerve
times and things paſt, and thence did wiſely gather and
foreſee what might be hereafter, and accordingly did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulate
his affairs, which day the Heathens did in like
manner ſolemnize, and alſo by ſending of New-years-gifts
one to another, wherefore the whole Catholike Church
(as Mr. <hi>Prin</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Hiſtriom. p. 756. Concil. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſiod. A. C. 614. Can. 1. Synodus Turonica 2 Can. 23. Concil. Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtant. 6. A. C. 680 Can. 62.</note> informs us out of <hi>Alcuvinus</hi>) and four
famous Councils appointed a ſolemn faſt to be kept on
that day, to bewaile all heatheniſh ſports, plays, and lewd
idolatrous practiſes and prophane courſes,<note place="margin">Polyd. Virgil de Invent. rerum l. 5. c. 2.</note> prohibiting all
Chriſtians under pain of Excommunication from obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
the firſt of <hi>January</hi> as holy, or ſending New years
gifts.<note place="margin">Durand. Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nale divin. offic. l. 6. c. 15.</note> 
               <hi>It was condemned alſo</hi> by many ancient and learned
Writers, as <hi>Ambroſe, Auguſtine, Chryſoſtome,</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
yea, and by two Popes as bad as they were, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<hi>Pope Zachary,</hi> and <hi>Pope Martin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>February</hi> the ſecond was dedicated to the honour of
their <hi>goddeſſe Februa,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rhenanus in Tertul de Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na militum.</note> (the mother of <hi>Mars,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Tertul. de I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolat.</note> another of
their Deities) to whom the <hi>Pagans</hi> offered burnt torches,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115207:4"/>
tapers, and wax-candles to pacifie the evill Spirits, as they
did alſo on the altars of <hi>Saturn,</hi> on his feſtivall days, and
the moneth is called <hi>February</hi> from <hi>Februus,</hi> which is
<hi>Pluto,</hi> the god of hell, as the heathens imagined.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May-day,</hi> the firſt day of <hi>May,</hi> was conſecrated and
kept in honour of their devill goddeſſe <hi>Flora,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Polyd. Virgil. de Invent. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, l. 5. c. 2.</note> a notable
rich whore, at what time they uſed to bring laurell, green
boughs and branches of trees and flowers, with ſinging
and rejoycing, and adorn their doors and houſes with
them, a heatheniſh idolatrous practiſe, condemned by
the Councill of <hi>Toledo,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Concil. Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanum A. C. 617 Can. 73.</note> where were preſent 77 Biſhops,
and by <hi>Pope Martin,</hi> and by many other good writers, yet
frequently practiſed in many places of <hi>England</hi> to this
day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The firſt of November,</hi> was ſolemnly kept by the <hi>Pagans,</hi>
in honour of all their devils Deities,<note n="n" place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 20</note> and a Temple built
in <hi>Rome,</hi> and conſecrated in honour of them, both that
feaſt and Temple were therefore called<note n="o" place="margin">Polyd. Virgil. de Invent. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, l. 6. c. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Pantheon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you have a brief account of ſome of the Pagan
idolatrous feſtivals, and how obſerved by them in honour
of their idoll devill gods, and conſequently how little rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
we Chriſtians have to obſerve them. Now</p>
            <p>2 To come neerer to the point in hand, we muſt know
alſo that the heathen idolatrous holy dayes were turned
into Chriſtian, as <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Nativity</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Polyd Virgil. de Invent. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, l. 5. c. 1, 2. Durandus Rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. divin. offic. l. 7. c. 34. in feſto omnium Sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, Franc. de Croy <hi>his firſt conformity c.</hi> 19. 20.</note> was appointed to be
kept, and hath long been generally obſerved on the very
time and day, when <hi>Saturns</hi> idolatrous, riotous feaſt was
ſolemnized, and in the room and imitation thereof, and
therefore that time was anciently called <hi>Yule</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the heathens called it, and the mad, ryotous, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane
playes, and ſports in <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> time, <hi>Yule-games</hi> and
<hi>Chriſtmas Karols,</hi> ſung in praiſe of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as the heathens
did the hymn <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in honour of the idoll <hi>Keres,</hi> that is
<hi>Ceres,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doctor</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. de anno Maced. &amp; p. 40. <hi>out of</hi> Beda, de ratione temporum.</note> goddeſſe of corn.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Innocents day Decemb.</hi> 28. The pretended day in which
the Innocent children of <hi>Bethlem</hi> were murthered by <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rods</hi>
command, <hi>Matt.</hi> 2. 16.) is dedicated to the memory,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115207:5"/>
and kept in honour of them, as it was conſecrated and
kept feſtivall in honour of the Pagans idoll god <hi>Quirinus</hi>
the ſirname of <hi>Romulus,</hi> the founder of <hi>Rome,</hi> whoſe idoll
feaſt is called <hi>Quirinalia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Circumciſion of Chriſt,</hi> was ſolemnized on <hi>Jaunary
the firſt,</hi> in the roome of their two-faced<note n="q" place="margin">Jani hiſrontis imago Virg. l. 7. Plutarch. in Numa Pompil. p. 48. Latinae verſionis Xy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landri. Jodo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us in Hora<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. f. 57.</note> idoll <hi>Janus</hi>
heatheniſh idolatrious-feſtivall, and from thence <hi>Yule</hi> an
hymne and ſheafe, (a burnt offering) to <hi>Ceres,</hi> our <hi>Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes
Chriſtmas Karols</hi> and ſending of New-yeares-gifts
came.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Purification of Mary,</hi> is celebrated on <hi>February</hi> the
ſecond, and called <hi>Candlemas-day,</hi> becauſe of the many
wax candles and tapers offer'd and burnt in honour of the
Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Polyd Virgil. de Invent. l. 5. c. 2.</note> and chriſtened by the <hi>Papiſt Candlemas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi>
as the Pagan Idolaters did on that day to their ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>god
<hi>Februa,</hi> more abundantly then to <hi>Saturn</hi> on his day,
but <hi>accendant quotidiè lucernas, quibus lux nulla eſt, let them
light candles to them that have no light in themſelves,</hi> ſaid <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi>
and <hi>Lactantius</hi> of the<note n="ſ" place="margin">Tertul. in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polog adverſus Gentes, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>actant. Inſtitut l. 6. c. 2.</note> heathens.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May-day,</hi> alſo hath been by us obſerved (by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
of Superiours as others holy days were) even with
the heathens cuſtomes of bringing green boughs, branches
of trees, flowers, and adorning of houſes, windows, with
them, juſt as the Heathens did, alſo <hi>May-poles,</hi> dancing,
drinking, and the like, <hi>Ethnicorum more,</hi> after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
of the idolatrous Pagans.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe, <hi>The firſt of November,</hi> was dedicated and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved
feſtivall in honour of the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> and all the
<hi>Saints,</hi> by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Polyd. Virgil. l. 6. c. 8. Durand. Rationale di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin o<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ic. Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delphus H<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian. de orig. ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorum Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. f. 159</note> and called <hi>All-Saints-day,</hi>
(as the Pagans obſerved it in honour of all the idol
gods calling it <hi>Pantheon</hi>) and that by the decrees of <hi>Pope
Boniface the Fourth,</hi> and <hi>Pope Gregory the Fourth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3 This change of Pagan idolatrous feaſts into Chriſtian,
in honour of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the Saints, was made by ſome of
the <hi>Ancients,</hi> when Chriſtianity was ſpread among the
Heathens, and many of them converted to the true faith,
in hope, that by complying with them, in obſerving their
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115207:5"/>
feſtivall days but to Chriſtian ends, they ſhould the rather
draw the Pagan Idolaters from Paganiſm to Chriſtianity.
<hi>Pope Teleſphonus</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Rabanas M<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urus I<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. Clericorum l 2. c. 31. ut r<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt Guil Prin Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om. p. 774. Miſſas in nocte Nativitacis Chriſti t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brari ſtatuit Teleſphorus. Summa Conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liorum &amp; Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificum per Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholom. Carran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zam, p. 17, 18. <hi>Doctor</hi> Fu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k <hi>in an<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wer to the</hi> Rhemiſh <hi>Teſt.</hi> Matth. 2. 5, 4.</note> who began about the year of Chriſt
140 in the time of <hi>Antoninus,</hi> the Emperours reign, was
the firſt Authour we read of among the <hi>Romans,</hi> of the
celebration of Chriſts Nativity, and on that day <hi>Saturns</hi>
devil-feaſt was began, <hi>viz. December</hi> the 25, but in other
Churches (excepting <hi>Conſtantinople</hi>) I find as yet no obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
of it, the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> where Antichriſt was
to reign, being the firſt beginner and authour as of moſt
other ſuperſtitious obſervations, ſo of this alſo. Before
<hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, there were not many feſtivals obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,
and the feaſt of the Nativity of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Eaſter and
Pentecoſt, which two laſt certainly (were obſerved before
the Nativity) were not univerſally obſerved till many
years after, ſaith Dr. <hi>Fulke,</hi> no not till many hundred
years after Chriſt, ſee <hi>Magdeburgenſis Century</hi> 2. 4. 5. 6.
<hi>Gregor. Magnus in Evang. hom. 8. Chemnit. harmony p.</hi> 92.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The other feaſts mentioned before, were changed by</hi>
Pope Boniface,<note n="x" place="margin">Bedae Eccleſ. hiſtor. l. 2 c. 14.</note> 
               <hi>and</hi> Pope Gregory the Firſt;<note n="y" place="margin">Greg. Magn. Ep. l. 9 Ep. 71.</note> Pope Boniface
<hi>began</hi> A. C. 419. Pope Gregorius <hi>began</hi> A. C. 590. <hi>as</hi>
Alſtedius <hi>and</hi> Bellarmine<note n="z" place="margin">Alſted. Chron. p. 279. Bellar. de Script. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ.</note> 
               <hi>inform me, contrary to the
judgment and will of renowned</hi> Ambroſe, Auguſtiue,
<hi>and the whole</hi> Councill of Affrick,<note n="a" place="margin">Guil. Prin hiſtr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om. p. 760.</note> Can. 27. 28. <hi>and others.
And to ſpeak truth at the firſt,</hi> Chriſts Nativity <hi>and other
feaſts was religiouſly obſerved by the Chriſtians. Hear</hi>
Tertullian <hi>of this matter,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tertull. in Apolog. adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Gentes c. 39, 40 f.</hi> 187. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently alſo to this purpoſe <hi>Greg. Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zene in orat. in Natalem Dom.</hi> A good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. for Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans now to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, on the Lords dayes, &amp; days of thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giv<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng.</note> 
               <hi>ſaith he, (ſpeaking of himſelf,
and the Chriſtians of his time.</hi>) Coimus in coetum, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregationem,
ut Deum quaſi manu facta precationibus ambia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus
orantes. Wee aſſemble together into one company, that ſo
we might, as it were, aſſault and beſiege God with our joynt
prayers. Again, we feed our faith, with holy words erect our hope,
ſettle our confidence, eſtabliſh our diſcipliue with the often in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcations
of divine precepts: alſo there are exhortations, corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,
divine cenſures. <hi>After which, they kept the Supper,
or</hi> Love-feaſt (Agape) <hi>in which</hi> nihil vilitatis, nihil immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtiae
admittur, non prius diſcumbitur quam oratio ad Deum
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115207:6"/>
praeguſtatur, <hi>in which,</hi> no vileneſſe, no immodeſty is admitted,
they ſate not down (to eat) before they had firſt ſent up a prayer
to God. Editur quantum eſurientes capiant, bibitur quantum
pudicii eſt utile, <hi>and then falling to their meat,</hi> they eat no
more then would well ſatisfie their hunger, drink no more than
was fit for modeſt perſons, ſatiating themſelves, ſo as they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred
they were to worſhip God in the night after. Ita confa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulantur
ut qui ſciunt Deum audire, diſcourſing as they who
well knew God heard them. Poſt aquam manualem, and after
water to waſh their hands, and lights were brought in, every one
as he was able, was provoked to ſing a Pſalm to God. And as
prayer began, ſo it likewiſe concluded the feaſt, after which they
departed non in catervas coeſionum, neque in claſſes diſcurſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onum,
nec in eruptiones laſcivorum, not into the rude routs of
ſwaſhing blades, not into the companies of rambling fellows, not
into the laſhings out of laſcivious perſons, but to the ſame care
of modeſty and chaſtity, like thoſe, qui non tam coenam coenave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint
quam diſciplinam, who had not ſo fed their bellies, as their
minds and hearts with wholeſome diſcipline. Thus he ſhews
how religiouſly they obſerved their feaſts; the ſuppoſed
day of Chriſt's Nativity, and other feſtivall days at firſt,
after their change from Pagan to Chriſtian feſtivals,
which ſtrict and religious obſervation of thoſe days, were
it now injoyned by authority, and practiſed, I believe it
would be as much diſliked by our Chriſtmas men, as the
non-obſervation of the time is now diſpleaſing.</p>
            <p>4 But then withall, it muſt be remembred, that within
a little time after, the obſervation of theſe Pagan feſtivall
days (though the name and end was changed) brought in
all the heatheniſh cuſtomes, and Pagan rites and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies
that the idolatrous Heathens uſed, as riotous Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
Health-drinking, Gluttony, Luxury, Wantonneſſe,
Dancing, Dicing, Stage-plays, Enterludes, Masks, Mum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meries,
with all other Pagan ſports, and prophane practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
into the Church of God, which was never defiled with
theſe prophane abominations, till thoſe Pagan holy days
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115207:6"/>
were changed into Chriſtian, which by reaſon of mens
naturall proceſſe to carnall pleaſures, and heatheniſh rites
and ceremonies, &amp;c. did ſoon transform all Chriſtian fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtivals
into heathen again, as many learned and good Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
aſſure us,<note n="b" place="margin">Vide Prins Hiſtricm. p. 760</note> till at laſt, all Chriſtendome was over-run
with them, and in a manner all life and power of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity
eaten out with thoſe Pagan Chriſtmas paſtimes and
heatheniſh delights. <hi>Hunc diem plurimi Chriſtianorum
diurnis nocturniſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> compotationibus, commeſſationibuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt,
ita ut non Chriſti Natalia, ſed Bacchanalia potius &amp;
Lupernalia agere viderentur, ſo that they ſeemed not to keep the
feaſt of Chriſt's Nativity:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſpinian de o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rig. feſt. Chriſt. f. 45. &amp; 159.</note> (the like may be ſaid of other ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
days) <hi>but rather the drunken and riotous feaſt of Idoll</hi> Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus
<hi>and</hi> Pan, as <hi>Hoſpinian</hi> truly ſaith. It is true alſo that
<hi>Beroaldus</hi> obſerveth,<note place="margin">Bercald. Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum, l. 4. c. 1.</note> that the pretence of celebrating the
memory and vertues of ſome eminent godly Chriſtians,
brought in holy dayes,<note place="margin">Primum ad o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium, d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inde ad nequitiam &amp; ad caetera quae otium alit ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, inducit.</note> and holy days idleneſſe, and idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
prophaneneſſe and all licentiouſneſſe, but we may
ſay of the obſervation of holy days, as our Saviour in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
caſe, <hi>from the beginning it was not ſo. The truth is,</hi>
that holy days, Monkery, Nunnery, ſolitary life, Images,
praying for the dead, prayer to Saints departed and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels
as Mediatours, were brought in by the factors for
Antichriſt, yet with ſuch ſpecious pretences, and ſeeming
devotion and holineſſe, that even many good men were
ſtrangely deceived by them, till it was too late to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
them. <hi>But by thoſe</hi> Chriſtmas ſports, carnall plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures
and delights, God hath in thoſe few holy days been
more diſhonoured, the devill better ſerved, evill men
more hardned in their wickedneſſe, and good men more
grieved, and more ſouls ſent head-long to hell, than on
any other day, yea, than on all the reſt of the year beſide.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherefore,</hi> thoſe godly Fathers, <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Auguſtine <hi>the father flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> A. C. 4: o <hi>died</hi> 433. B<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llar de Script Eccleſ. Alſt<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d. Chronolog.</note> and others,
obſerving thoſe growing evils that followed thereupon,
wiſhed Pagan feſtivals had never been turned into Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
feaſts, but quite aboliſhed, the better to avoid all
heatheniſh cuſtomes, diſſolute and prophane practiſes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:115207:7"/>
And although the diſorders and abuſes of thoſe days
were afterward condemned by <hi>Councils</hi> and <hi>Synods,</hi> as
by the <hi>Councill</hi> of <hi>Rhemes, A. C.</hi> 1583, by the <hi>Synod
of Toures in France,</hi> the ſame year, and by others before
and ſince, yet all in vain, no rooting of them out, but by
taking away the obſervation of them wholly, as experience
ſheweth.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee who firſt appointed thoſe holy days we
formerly kept as holy feſtivities, <hi>viz.</hi> the Heathen Pagan
Idolaters, in honour of their idol devill gods, the ſouls of
ſome dead Heroes, which all Chriſtians ought to abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate,
and that long after ſuch idolatrous uſe of them,
ſome ſeducing and ſeduced Chriſtians turned the ſame
days into Chriſtian feſtivals in honour of Chriſt and the
Saints, in complyance with the Heathen Idolaters, out of
hope to draw them to a Chriſtian Religion, but though the
corruption of mans nature, eſpecially they having no divine
warrant from <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> ſo to do, it turned to the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
of the Heathens in their Idolatry, and the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall
and abominable corruption of the Church of
Chriſt.</p>
            <p>5 Now let it be conſidered, whether Chriſt was
born as on that day, which commonly goes under his
name, or about that time, and ſurely upon inquiry,
wee ſhall finde that hee was not born then, but rather
about the end of <hi>September,</hi> in <hi>October,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Hoſpinian. de orig. feſt. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia. Matthaei Beroaldi Chron. <hi>l. 4 c</hi> 12. Hen. Wolphius in Ch<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>The Jews Ch<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſtian</hi> aera <hi>or a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>coun<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> birth of Chriſt beginni<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g in</hi> September, Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus S<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aliger de Emend. tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porum, Hugh Broughten <hi>in his Conſent of Scripture, in</hi> A. M. 3953. Jo ban. Canſabon. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. p. 91. Scaliger <hi>a ſo in</hi> Canonibus Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is, p. 297. Mr. M<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triba 3. part. p. 617. &amp;c A<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſted. Praecog. T<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ol. p. 532 &amp; 572. Alſted. Chronol p. 19. 22 74. &amp; 120. Encyclop. p 2998. <hi>Who addeth further,</hi> ut docent e<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uditi Chronol<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gi. <hi>It is the opinion of the moſt learned Chronologers, ſaith Mr.</hi> Mead, Di<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>triba 3<hi rend="sup">
                     <hi>d</hi>.</hi> port p. 6. 8. <hi>Doctor</hi> Drakes <hi>ſacred Chronog.</hi> p. 72, 73. Scharpius Symphon. Veteres animad vert<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe Dominum noſtrum Jeſum Chriſtum, natum fuiſſe aquinoctio Autum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nali, quae canſa eſt ut annos inde ſic exorſiprioris aetatis Chriſtiani, quos à Domini nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate ſolita eſt inc<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oare Vetus Eccleſia. <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>roaldi Chron. l. 4. p.</hi> 236.</note> which I thus
clear, beſide the learned Authors judgment mentioned
in the margine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> from the time of his conception, which was to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
the end of <hi>December,</hi> or in <hi>Ianuary</hi> at the fartheſt,
and therefore his birth being full 9 moneths or 40 weeks
after, muſt fall about the end of <hi>September,</hi> or in <hi>October</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:115207:7"/>
which I think evident, by laying down theſe Propoſitions,
which I believe are manifeſt truths.</p>
            <p>1 That the Jews Eccleſiaſticall year began in <hi>Niſan,</hi>
alias <hi>Abib, Exod 12. 2. This moneth ſhall be to you the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
of moneths,</hi> the moneth in which <hi>Iſrael</hi> came out of
Egypt, <hi>Exod.</hi> 13. 4. which contains the latter part of our
March, and the former part of our Aprill.</p>
            <p>2 That the Jewiſh year conſiſted of twelve moneths.</p>
            <p>3 That in thoſe 12 monethes were 24 courſes for the
Prieſts to ſerve in the Temple, each Prieſt fourteen days,
1 <hi>Chron 24. v.</hi> 1, and 6. to 20.</p>
            <p>4 That in <hi>Abiatus</hi> courſe,<note n="c" place="margin">Alſted. Chron. p. 19, 20, 74.</note> which was the eighth
courſe or fortnight from the beginning of <hi>Abib,</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan
on the latter part of our March, with our March<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moon
then.</p>
            <p>That miſtake that <hi>Zechary</hi> was high Prieſt, and offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated
in September, in the feaſt of Tabernacles may eaſily
be confuted from the text, <hi>Luke 1. v.</hi> 1, 8, 9. the primitive
practiſe of the Church of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> which was very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act
in their accounts, they celebrated the birth of <hi>Iohn</hi> the
Baptiſt, Aprill 2<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 13 the 28 <hi>menſis Pharmutii,</hi> ſaith <hi>Cyrill,</hi>
in an Homily on that occaſion. Alſo by the perpetuall
obſervation of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and is fully done by <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>harpius,
Scaliger, Cauſabon, Ber<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ldus, Mead,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Scharpi Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon. p. 471. Cauſahon <hi>out</hi> Scaliger. Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit. p. 91. Berc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ald. Chron. l. 4. c. 2. Meads Dia <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> triba 3 pa t. p. 620.</note> and others.</p>
            <p>5 That after <hi>Zecharies</hi> courſe of miniſtring in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
was ended, and <hi>Zechary</hi> returned home, his wife <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi>
conceived him, who was after called <hi>John, Luke</hi> 1.
5, 6, 13, 19, 23, 24, <hi>After theſe days,</hi> (that is, the end of his
courſe and miniſtery) <hi>his wife Elizabeth conceived, &amp;c.</hi>
which was in the latter end of our July, and <hi>John</hi> was
born in the end of our Aprill<note n="f" place="margin">Scharp. Sym. phon. p. 473. Alſted. Chron p. 20. 74. 121. Brough<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ons <hi>Conſent in</hi> A. M. 3953. Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſabon <hi>out of</hi> Scaliger. de E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendatione temporum, &amp; in Canonibus Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is. p. 29<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cauſa<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercitati, p 91.</note> or thereabout.</p>
            <p>6 That our bleſſed Saviour was conceived in the
wombe of the <hi>Virgin Mary</hi> by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> ſix moneths
after the conception of <hi>John the Baptiſt, Luke</hi> 1. 7, 26, 27,
to 36. which muſt fall out about the end of December,
or in January ſix moneths after the end of July, the time
of <hi>Johns</hi> conception.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:115207:8"/>
Theſe things being granted (w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> I think cannot be denied)
it muſt of neceſſity follow that Chriſts birth, which was
nine moneths or forty weeks after, muſt fall out about the
end of September, or in October, eſpecially he being her
firſt-born.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I clear this aſſertion concerning the time of
<hi>Chriſt</hi>'s birth, from the time of his ſuffering, thus:</p>
            <p>1 It is (I think) generally granted by Divines,<note place="margin">Matthaeus Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roald. Chron l. 4. c. 2. &amp; l. 3. c. 8.</note> that
<hi>Chriſt</hi> lived on earth 32 years and an half, or 33 and an
half, <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s birth and baptiſme were both on the 14 day
of the ſeventh moneth, to which our September anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth:
he was three year and an half in his miniſtry, lived
in all 32 years and an half (ſaith <hi>Beroaldus</hi>) but many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
reckon 33 years and an half;<note place="margin">g Piſcator in Luk. 3. 13 Beza, Broughtons <hi>Conſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> A. M. 3941. Lauren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tii C<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>doman. Annales. Ainſw. Annot. in Numb 4. 3. <hi>with</hi> Gen. 5. 32. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eroal<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i Chron. l. 4. c. 2.</note> all (I think) acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
an odde half year, for he was baptized and entred
into his publique miniſtery, when he began to be, or entred
upon the thirtieth year of his age. <hi>Luke</hi> 3. 22, 23. at which
age the Leviticall Prieſts (as ſome affirm) enter'd upon
their ſervice. <hi>Numb.</hi> 4. 3, 35, 39, 43, 47. or as ſome others
when the thirtieth year of his age was compleat, and he
began to enter upon his one and thirtieth year, the words
are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which word for word is: <hi>he was begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
&amp;c. Beroaldus</hi> renders it thus: <hi>Ipſe annum ingreditur
triceſſimum:</hi> ſee the Authors in the Margine.</p>
            <p>2 That hee lived three years and an half in his pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique
miniſtery, from his baptiſme to his paſſion, is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
granted by Divines, yet ſome,<note n="h" place="margin">Alſted. Chron. p. 22. Scharpius in Sympho. p. 474.</note> I have read, ſay four
years and an half,<note place="margin">i Laurentius Codoman. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nales, H. B. &amp; R. B. Iti<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſacrae Script p. 477. Auguſt. contra Judaeos, Paganos, Arria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos, l. 3. c. 5.</note> which diſagreement doth nothing wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
our aſſertion, but confirm it.</p>
            <p>3 T<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he ſuffered the 15 day of the moneth <hi>Abib</hi> or
<hi>Nilan,</hi> which was then about our Aprill the third, but
<hi>Auſtine</hi> ſays on the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Kalends of April (that is March 25.</p>
            <p>Now caſt away all the whole years (be they more or
fewer, it matters not) and there remains half a year or ſix
moneths, which all learned men (w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> I have read or heard
of acknowledg) which ſix moneths reckon (either forward
or backward, all comes to one account) from the time of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115207:8"/>
his ſuffering and his birth falleth preciſely about the end
of September or beginning of October, and ſo we have
the time evidenced to fall out this way alſo pat with the
other. This alſo <hi>Beroaldus</hi> proveth from the 9 of<note n="k" place="margin">Math. B<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rcal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di Chron<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>corum l. 4. c. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Daniel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Neer upon the ſame time falleth the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of Mr. <hi>Mead,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Meads Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triba 3. part p. 615. &amp; 617. Hen. Wolphius in Chron.</note> and ſome others from <hi>John 1. 14. The
word was made fleſh, and dwelt among us:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>;
and tabernacled, pitched his tent, or dwelt in tents, for ſo
the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifieth, anſwerable to the type of
the Iſraelites, dwelling in tabernacles, tents or buſhes
in the feaſt of the ſeventh moneth, <hi>Levit. 23. 34. Deut.</hi> 16.
13. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 8. 14, a thing uſuall among the Jews, at the
feaſts of Tabernacles, which began on the 15 day of the
September-moon, and ended the 22, at which time they
affirm <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be born, and ſo happily anſwered the type,
which another cuſtome uſed at that feaſt, ſeems to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm,
for while they were carrying the boughs, they uſed
this ſhort prayer, <hi>Hoſanna, Hoſanna, a ſave now,</hi> or <hi>ſave
I beſeech thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Adde here unto the teſtimony of the <hi>Rabbines</hi>
in <hi>Midraſh Rabba,</hi> that the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> muſt be born in the
moneth <hi>Aethanim,</hi> alias <hi>Tiſri,</hi> and September <hi>the moneth
of ſtrengths,</hi> full of feaſts, to teach of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> And ſo
wee finde that the three chief aniverſary feaſts of the
Jews did foretell and type out <hi>Chriſts</hi> times.</p>
            <p>As 1 <hi>Their Paſſeover</hi> was a memoriall of <hi>Iſraels</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation
in Egypt, and deliverance out of it in the firſt
moneth <hi>Abib,</hi> fitly prefiguring Chriſts death, and our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall
redemption wrought by Chriſt at the ſame time.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Their feaſt of Weeks,</hi> or harveſt 50 days after the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over,
the time of giving the <hi>fiery law</hi> by <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Iſrael</hi>
with our <hi>Pentecoſt,</hi> when the Spirit was given in fiery
cloven tongues. <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 1, 2, 3, 4. So</p>
            <p>3 <hi>Their feaſt of Tabernacles,</hi> or dwelling in tents or
buſhes on 15 of the ſeventh moneth, and September, 8
days together, prefigured <hi>Chriſts Nativity,</hi> pitching his
tent, or dwelling in the Tabernacle of his fleſh among
men, four times eight years.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:115207:9"/>
               <hi>Fiftly,</hi> At that time Chriſt was born, all the world
went to be taxed, every man to his own city, <hi>Luke</hi> 2. 2, 3.
but it is not at all probable, that the journeying of all the
world, men and women with child, ſhould be comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
by Empericall Edict in the depth of winter, when
the ways were worſt, and the days ſhorteſt, and therefore
unfitteſt for travail, eſpecially for women with child, there
are days enough in the year beſide to gather and pay mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney:
neither was <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> ſo bare of money and
hard put to it: neither doth Princes uſe to gather ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary
taxes of their ſubjects in the middle of win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
and when the fruits of the year are half ſpent, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
after harveſt,<note place="margin">Hen. Wolph. Chron. l. 1.</note> as <hi>Wolphius</hi> obſerveth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixtly,</hi> At that Chriſt was born, the Shepheards were
watching their flocks in the open fields all night, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.
8. but tis very unprobable, that they did ſo in winter,
eſpecially in December moneth, ſheep being <hi>frigoris impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientiſſimae,</hi>
moſt impatient of cold, as <hi>H. Wolphius</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">H Wolp<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. l. 1. Chron.</note> out
of <hi>Heſide l. 2. operum,</hi> but in houſes or ſtables, as <hi>Columella</hi>
ſaith. <hi>l. 7. c. 3. &amp; Virgil. l. 3. Georg.</hi> conſider our Saviours
words. <hi>Matth. 24. 20. Pray that your flight be not in the
winter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> Neither is it likely, that the Wiſemen that
came to viſite Chriſt, were ſo unwiſe, as to take ſo long
a journey to, and from Chriſt, in the<note n="n" place="margin">Doct <hi>Drakes</hi> ſacred <hi>Chron. p.</hi> 72.</note> depth of winter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eighthly,</hi> Chriſt was born on the day of the Autumme
Equinoctiall, in which the world was made by God, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
and undone by <hi>Adam,</hi> but renewed by<note n="o" place="margin">Natus mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus &amp; renatus eodem menſe ſc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptimo, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ald. Chron. l. 4. p. 248. <hi>See</hi> Hen. Wolphius Chr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. l. 1.</note> Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ninthly, Beroaldus</hi> proves Chriſt birth to be in Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
by another argument from <hi>Daniel c.</hi> 9. in his 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.
<hi>Book,</hi> and 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
               <hi>chapt</hi> to whom I referre the learned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> The true, perticular and exact time of Chriſts
birth cannot be determined by men, and if Chriſts birth
were unknown to<note n="p" place="margin">Clem. Alex. Strom. l. 1. <hi>who lived</hi> An. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti, 195. Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius, Beroal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus, Mead, <hi>Dr.</hi> Fulk <hi>on the</hi> Rhem. <hi>Teſt.</hi> Matth 2. 5, 1.</note> 
               <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi> and them that
lived the next age to Chriſt, why, I pray you (ſaith <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpinian</hi>)
do you believe <hi>Epiphanius,</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Epiph. to<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. l 2.</note> who lived almoſt
400 years after, who held January 5, or <hi>Middelburgenſis,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:115207:9"/>
who<note n="r" place="margin">Middelburg c. 4. l. 19.</note> was for the 8 Kalends of Aprill, is March 25, or
they that ſay he was born on December 25. as did <hi>Oroſius?</hi>
Some of the Ancients held that Chriſt was born January 6,
and they call'd <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, alſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſome on April 29:
ſome on <hi>May</hi> 19, or 20: ſome in September, ſome on De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember
25, ſaith <hi>Hoſpinian,</hi> and <hi>I. Cauſabon,</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Hoſpin. de ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine feſt. Chriſt. Cauſabon. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercit. 1. p 91.</note> ſome on March
25, then the day of the Vernall Equinoctiall, ſaith <hi>Middel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgenſis.</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Middelburg. l. 19. c. 4.</note> And accordingly, the birth of Chriſt was ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated
by the Roman, or Latine and French Churches
on December 25, ſaith <hi>Theophilus Caeſarienſis, Paleſtinae
Epiſcopus.</hi> The <hi>Aegyptians, Graecians</hi> and <hi>Armenians,</hi> a
people in <hi>Aſia,</hi> celebrated his Nativity and Baptiſme,
both together on our <hi>Epiphany,</hi> January 6, ſaith <hi>Caſſianus</hi>
and <hi>Hugo,</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Hugo in Matth. c. 1.</note> others on the 15 day of <hi>menſis <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yb.</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
January 9, ſome others on the 14 or 15 <hi>menſis Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muthi,</hi>
that is Aprill the 9 or 10, as <hi>Cyrill</hi> informs us in an
Homily on that<note n="*" place="margin">Cyril in hom. ejus argumenti.</note> occaſion.</p>
            <p>The firſt inſtitution of it cannot be known, ſaith <hi>Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi>
and the firſt mention of its obſervation that he could
finde (though a diligent ſearcher into Antiquities of this
kind) was by <hi>Theophilus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Paſch. Epiſt.</note> Saint <hi>Theophilus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och.
A long time after</hi> the <hi>Lords</hi> Aſcenſion, there was no day
or certain time appointed for the obſervation of the birth
of Chriſt, ſaith <hi>Beroaldus,</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Beroa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, Chro. l. 4 p. 238. longo poſt Aſcentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Domini tempore nullum fuiſſe feſtum, aut cer<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore diſtinctam diei natalis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervationem.</note> yea, there was no certainty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed
upon in <hi>Epiphanius</hi> time, as himſelf witneſſeth, who
lived almoſt 400 years after Chriſt; and it was after the
time of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great (who died about 337) that
the 25 of December, was choſen, and firſt in the Latine or
Roman Church, but not in the Greek Church till the
days of <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Maſt<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r</hi> Mead Diatriba. 3. part. p. 619.</note> who made an oration, yet extant,
at the firſt obſervation of that day, which he ſays they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
from the Roman Church, he flouriſhed <hi>A. C.</hi> 400.
But <hi>Beroaldus</hi> ſaith,<note n="z" place="margin">Beroald Chron. l. 4. c. 1. p. 236. &amp; 238. Hoſpin. de orig ſeſt. Chriſt. f. 66</note> there was nothing certain inſtituted
til <hi>A. C.</hi> 532, and that, as it ſeems, the firſt Councill that
determin'd that day, was the <hi>Council of Aurelia,</hi> or <hi>Orleans</hi>
in <hi>France A. C.</hi> 558, and after that the 10 <hi>Councils of Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do
in Spain, A C.</hi> 621, but it was obſerved long before that,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115207:10"/>
and ſurely God hath purpoſely concealed that day of
Chriſts birth, that none might ſuperſtitiouſly obſerve it,
as he did <hi>Moſes</hi> ſepulcher.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> But if Chriſt's birth was about the end of Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
or in October, why then did the Ancients ſet that time
apart in memory of Chriſt's birth, and not ſome other
neereſt to it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Ancients,</hi> who changed that Pagan feſtivall to
Chriſts Nativity, did not therefore pitch on that day, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
they thought he was then both, ſaith <hi>Hoſpinian, Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus
Jovius,</hi> and others, eſpecially <hi>J. Cauſabon,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Hoſpin de o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rig. feſt. Chriſt. f. 160. Paulus Jovius biſt. l. 38 Hugo in Matth. c. 2. Cauſobon. Exercit. 1. p. 91. Videntur Pii Patres, &amp;c. Religionem fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilius admiſſum iri ſperabant ſi eadem opera im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pias Gentium ſolemni ates de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berent &amp; novas inſt<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tuerent, quae ad verum Dei cultum p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent.</note> but becauſe
they hoped that the turning the Heathens feaſts on theſe
days w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> were obſerved to chriſtian, as they did alſo ſome
other Pagan holy-days, obſerving the ſame days ſtill, but
to a better end and uſe, would be a means to draw the
Ethnicks from Paganiſm, to Chriſtianity, but it turned to
a quite contrary effect, to wit, the hardning of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens
in their idolatry and ways of ſin, and the great cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption
of the Church of God with heatheniſh cuſtomes,
prophane and ſuperſtitious practiſes, through the prone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
of people generally to carnall pleaſures, ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
and prophane cuſtomes and practiſes, and eſpecially
through the idleneſſe, luxury, pompe, power, wealth
and diſſoluteneſſe of the Popes clergy, the ſuperſtitious
Prieſts and Monks of <hi>Rome</hi> Chriſtian, (now long ſince tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
Antichriſtian) following ſtep by ſtep <hi>Rome</hi> Heathen,
who brought in and countenanced <hi>Spurcitias Gentilium,</hi>
the filthineſſe, diſhoneſty and uncleanneſſe of the idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous
Gentiles, as many good Authors and<note n="b" place="margin">Salvion. de Gubern. Dei, l. 3 Greg. Magnus hom. 17. in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangel. &amp; Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. l. 6. c. 17. Aug. de Civit. D<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i l. 2. c. 20. Franc. de Croy, <hi>his firſt confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity.</hi> Synodus Tironenſis ſub C<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arl. Magno, A. C. 742. Can. 5 Jeffery Chaucer <hi>his Plowmans tale. See many others mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in Maſter</hi> Prins Hiſtriom. p. 760. &amp;c. <hi>which I have not read.</hi>
               </note> Councils
inform us.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I conclude this ſection, that conformity un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,
and retention of the Heatheniſh cuſtomes in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation
of days, and perticularly of thoſe days firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated
to Heathens ſpurious idoll Deities, is not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable
in Chriſtians, ſutable or agreeable to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell,
though under pretext of honouring Chriſt, and his
worſhip, but to be renounced and caſt off for ever, with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation
of all Chriſtian pious hearts.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:115207:10"/>
6 <hi>But ſuppoſe it were true,</hi> and certain that Chriſt was
born in the <hi>Winter Solſtice,</hi> on that day we heretofore ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved
in memory of his birth, <hi>viz.</hi> December 25, (the
contrary whereunto is, I think, clearly and fully proved)
yet now by reaſon that our year conſiſteth of 365 days
and 6 hours is longer then the true naturall and tropicall
year, by 11 minutes and 15 ſeconds, or thereabout, every
25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day of December is ſo much later then the former, ſo
that the 25 of December this preſent year 1650 fals out
about thirteene days, or more later than the true ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
of time, and later than it was, then which
<hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> inſtituted the <hi>Julian-Yeare</hi> (the ſame
yeare that is now in uſe among us) about 54 years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<hi>Chriſt</hi> was born, alſo later by almoſt ſo much, then it
was on that year <hi>Chriſt</hi> was born, therefore our 25 of
December is not the day, but December 11, when the
Sun enters into <hi>Capricorn,</hi> (though the former ſuppoſition
were granted, which may not be) and therefore not to be
obſerved in memory of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> eſpecially by knowing
Chriſtians, leaſt by their practiſe they ſhould teach others
alſo to believe that for truth which is very untrue, that
Chriſt was born on that day, by which alſo we may ſee
how untruly though ignorantly many did ſay the Collect
appointed for that day. <hi>Almighty God which haſt given us
thine onely begotten ſon, to take our nature upon him, and</hi> this
day <hi>to be born, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>7 The celebration of our December the 25 in memory of
<hi>Chriſts Nativity</hi> (ſuppoſing further that he was then born,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>M.</hi> Cartwrights Annotat. <hi>on the</hi> Rhem. <hi>Teſt.</hi> Gal. 10. §. 5. Matth. 2. Sect. 1</note>
and that that time is the true time of the year, and the
ſame time it was when <hi>Chriſt</hi> was born, <hi>viz.</hi> the day of the
<hi>Winters Solſtice</hi>) yet is it not juſtifiable and warrantable for
Chriſtians who pretend to honour Chriſt to obſerve it.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Becauſe</hi> there is no precept, example, or approved
ground in ſacred Scripture for the obſervation of that day
in houour of <hi>Chriſts birth,</hi> if any ſuch be, let him that can
ſhew it, and I will imbrace it, and recant my errour at
<hi>Pauls-croſſe,</hi> or the <hi>Exchange,</hi> but it is an humane inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
and a meer tradition of men, and was deviſed, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115207:11"/>
the religious obſervation of it, and other holy days were
impoſed and commanded meerly and only by man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
any ground and warrant from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> therefore they
that will honour <hi>Chriſt,</hi> (as all ought to do) muſt not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
it or them, being without <hi>Chriſts</hi> direction. It is an
honour peculiar to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> to preſcribe times, days
and worſhips, and an high intrenching on his Sovereign
Authority and Kingly office, to preſcribe days and times,
therefore what <hi>Chriſt</hi> our <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Maſter</hi> doth not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,
or allow warrant to do, we may not do, we may not
obſerve days or times without his appointment and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,
but punctually (as neer as we can) keep to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,
<hi>Deut.</hi> 5. 32, 3<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Jerem. 7. 22 Iſaiah</hi> 1. 12. Therefore
Dr.<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Fulk.</hi> in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the <hi>Rhem.</hi> Teſt. on <hi>Luk.</hi> 24. 50.</note> 
               <hi>Fulk</hi> ſpeaking of the ſigne of croſſe in baptiſme ſaith,
<hi>It cannot be a memoriall of Chriſts, becauſe Chriſt commanded
it not,</hi> and ſo may I ſay of this, and all other the like ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
days.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Becauſe</hi> theſe days have been and are elſewhere to
this day greatly abuſed to all manner of prophaneneſſe,
diſſoluetneſſe and ſuperſtition, whereby God hath been
more diſhonoured on the Chriſtmas dayes, and ſo on all
other holy dayes alſo, and the Devil more ſerved, than at
any other time of the year, yea than on all the reſt of the
year beſide, therefore they are to be aboliſhed, as <hi>Hezeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi>
did the Brazen Serpent when abuſed to Idolatry, he
brake it into pieces, and called it <hi>Nehuſtan,</hi> a contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
piece of braſſe, though at firſt ſet up by Gods eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
command for an excellent end, and did much good,
2 <hi>Kings 18. 4. Tertullian</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Tertull. de Corona Milit</note> proves at large in his book <hi>of
the crown of ſouldiers, that when lawfull things are abuſed by
Pagans or Idolaters, Chriſtians may not uſe them, unleſſe they
have Gods warrant for them.</hi> And <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſhews.<note n="f" place="margin">Aug. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 86. ad Caſub.</note> 
               <hi>That
the Church of Chriſt left off to faſt on the Lords day, becauſe
the</hi> Manichees <hi>had taken up that day to faſt on.</hi> Alſo <hi>Biſhop
Jewell,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jewels</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie, <hi>p.</hi> 441.</note> gives many like examples, yea, and the very
Popes law<note n="h" place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pes Law diſtinct. 63. <hi>Quia Sancta.</hi>
               </note> reſolveth; <hi>That if our Predeceſſours have done
things well in their time, and afterward they be turned to er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115207:11"/>
or ſuperſtition, they muſt without any delay be reformed:</hi>
Indeed things neceſſary, though formerly groſly abuſed,
as houſes, churches, wine, &amp;c. may not therefore be abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed
or laid aſide, but the abuſe removed, as the Popiſh
abuſes and corruptions in both the Sacraments, &amp;c. but
things only lawful, unneceſſary, and not commanded of
God, ought to be aboliſhed when groſly abuſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beſide, let it be alſo remembred,</hi> that many of our Engliſh
or rather of Romiſh holy dayes were dedicated to
<hi>Saints,</hi> as the names of the days do witneſſe, as St. <hi>Stephen,</hi>
St. <hi>John,</hi> St. <hi>Peter,</hi> St. <hi>James, Innocents-day,</hi> &amp;c. which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone
maketh the retention and obſervation of them ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
and Idolatrous.</p>
            <p>3 <hi>Becauſe</hi> the obſervation of this feaſt, and other holy
days (ſo called) is now againſt the command of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream
Authority and Magiſtracy, in this Land, as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
of the <hi>Ordinances</hi> of both Houſes of Parliament do
witneſſe, and is wel known. <hi>And doubtleſſe,</hi> we are in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
bound to obey Authority in all things lawful, and do
ſin in a wilful diſobeying them. <hi>Rom. 13. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. 1 Pet.</hi> 2.
13, 14, 15, and do herein plainly contradict at leaſt in
practiſe, their proceedings in order to Reformation.</p>
            <p>4 Becauſe our ſolemn League and Covenant <hi>binds us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
an oath,</hi> To endeavour the extirpation of Popery, Prelacy,
Superſtition, Hereſie, Schiſme, Prophaneſſe and whatſoever ſhall
be found to be contrary to ſound doctrine and the power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe,
leaſt we pertake in other mens ſins, &amp;c. <hi>And ſure I
am the obſervation of theſe Heatheniſh, Popiſh holy days,
comes under ſome of theſe heads, and ſo under our Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
to reform.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5 <hi>The Jewiſh traditions</hi> of the Elders, as of waſhing
pots, cups, hands &amp;c. received from their fore-fathers
without warrant from Gods Word, for the religious ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation
of them, though with good intention, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved
and condemned by our Saviour,<note n="i" place="margin">Mark 7. 3, 4, 7, 8, 9.</note> therefore the
obſervation of theſe alſo is juſtly reproveable,<note place="margin">Matth. 15. 2, 3, 5, 7, 13.</note> being meer
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115207:12"/>
inventions of men, and having been groſly abuſed and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaned.</p>
            <p>6 <hi>The Jewiſh ceremoniall dayes,</hi> and obſervations though
commanded of God himſelf under the law, are now long
ſince aboliſhed, and unlawfull for Jews (much more for
Chriſtians under the Goſpel) and as a burthen too heavy
for their fore-fathers to bear, therefore much more the
religious obſervation of theſe days, which are onely the
commandements of men, as unlawfull for us Chriſtians,
Gentiles.</p>
            <p>7 <hi>Becauſe</hi> the obſervation of them is a conformity to
Pagan and Popiſh cuſtomes and practiſes, which a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
ought to abhorre and abominate, and flee from them
as much as may be, inſtance in leſſer matters than this, the
cutting off the hair of the head, beard, and the like, though
otherwiſe lawfull enough, meerly becauſe Idolaters did
ſo. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 19. 27, 28.</p>
            <p>8 <hi>Chriſtians are</hi> not bound to rejoyce at the birth of
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> on that 25 day of December, which many ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiouſly
call <hi>Chriſt-mas day</hi> more than at other times,
therefore neither to obſerve it more than any other day.</p>
            <p>9 <hi>The very name,</hi> with which the Pope and Papiſts
have chriſtened it <hi>Chriſt-mas,</hi> is enough to make all true
Chriſtians to abhorre the obſervation of it <hi>Chriſt-mas,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
the Papiſts had on that day a peculiar <hi>Maſſe</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendly
in honour of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but to his great diſhonour, it
being a moſt deteſtable <hi>Maſſe of Idolatry,</hi> in divers perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars,
as theſe Proteſtant Divines writing againſt the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts
doctrines, do unanimouſly affirm, and ſome have ſet them out<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>See Dr.</hi> Barns Du Pleſſis. <hi>Biſhop</hi> Jewell. &amp; alios quàm plurimos.</note> perticularly.</p>
            <p>10 <hi>The 4 Commandement</hi> enjoyns us <hi>to work on the ſix
days, and keep holy the ſeventh day. Exod.</hi> 20. 8, 9, 10. ſo that
if we obſerve Gods Commandement, there is no room left
for holy dayes, dayes of idleneſſe, ſuperſtition, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But it may be, ſome will ſay, is there not room
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115207:12"/>
for <hi>Chriſts-day,</hi> and other hoyldayes, as well as for dayes
of faſting and thankeſgiving?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No, becauſe to faſt on ſome ſpeciall occaſion<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, we
have not onely an old Teſtament,<note n="l" place="margin">Joel 1. 14, 15. &amp; 2. 12. to 18. Iſa. 58. begin.</note> but alſo a new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
1 A Goſpell approbation. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 16, 17, 18. 2 A
Goſpel command. <hi>Mat.</hi> 9. 15. 3 A Goſpel example. <hi>Acts
13. 2, 3. So</hi> for dayes of thankſgiving we have ſufficient
warrant from Gods Word. <hi>Pſal. 50. 14, 15. Exod. 15.
2 Chron. 20. 26, 27. Heſter</hi> 4. 16. and 9. 17, 18, 19, 20. but
we have neither Scripture precept, approbation, nor pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe
for keeping of this nor the other holy days.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But ſome have ſaid, Our fathers and fore-fathers
for many hundred years have obſerved theſe days, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<hi>Chriſtmas, Eaſter</hi> and <hi>Whitſontide,</hi> and the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of them hath been approved by <hi>Parliaments, Councils,</hi>
and <hi>Synods,</hi> and are now grown wiſer than all thoſe that
we ſhould now reject them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I much reverence and honour Parliament Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils,
and Synods and forefathers, but they were but men,
as we are, and did erre fouly, witneſſe the eſtabliſhing of
Popery, the Maſſe, praying for the dead, praying to Saints,
Angels, Images, Pictures and the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> yea, and adoring
and worſhipping of them, and of ſome Saints, Saints
Bones; cloathes and other Reliques. 2 They lived in
times of leſſe meanes of knowledge and more ignorance,
we of more means and knowledge. 3 As godly and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
and wiſe men have in all ages diſallowed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
the obſervation of theſe dayes, as any that allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
approved of them. <hi>And</hi> ſo hath our late Engliſh Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly
of Divines and Parliament alſo done, whom (I
beleeve) are as pious and learned as ever any in any, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
age in this Nation. 4 The matter is not who is
moſt learned, pious, and judicious but which party hath
Gods Word on their ſide and ſound reaſon, and for this
let the judicious Reader judge by what I have ſaid, I mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie
not my ſelf, but deſire to prefer the wiſedome and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115207:13"/>
Authority of God before and above all mens whatſoever,
and ſo far only follow me as I have Gods Word for my
warrant; <hi>homo ſum, errare poſſum, at haereticus eſſe nolo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> But is it not meet, that a day ſhould be ſet a part in
hand of <hi>Chriſt</hi> our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes, very fit, but it muſt be only that day which
himſelfe hath appointed and ſanctified to that end, and
therefore called it by his own name, to appropriate it to
himſelfe, <hi>viz: The Lords day, Revel.</hi> 1. 10. and hath
commanded us <hi>to remember to keep it holy, Ex<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> 20. 8, 9, 10.
<hi>Remember the Sabboth day to keep it holy,</hi> (is the day of
reſt,) <hi>the Sabboth of the Lord thy God,</hi> we may not ſet dayes
a part of our own head and without his minde, <hi>Neither</hi>
may any impoſe the obſervation of any day for this end,
leaſt they be found to be Intruders of humane inventions,
in ſtead of Gods Commandements on the conſciences of
Gods people, whereof <hi>Chriſt</hi> only is King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But many have religiouſly obſerved theſe dayes in
preaching, hearing, praying, ſinging, holy conference, &amp;c.
And have gotten much good thereby,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> True, but ten to one have got more hurt and done
more evil in theſe dayes, than on any other time, contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
more guilt, and done <hi>Chriſt</hi> more diſhonour than on
all other dayes. Beſides, the obſervation of dayes and
times, without Gods warrant, and greviouſly abuſed to
ſupperſtition and prophaneſſe, is not lawfull for Chriſtians
on pretence of ſome good gotten by duties of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
on thoſe dayes, which may as well be on any other
dayes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But ſome ſay ſtill, I ſee no hurt in them, they offend
not me, I obſerve them out of love and duty to my <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,</hi>
and with a good intention and well meaning, I do no
hurt to any man, and therefore I hope it is no offence to
Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Good intentions and wel meanings cannot juſtifie
any unwarrantable practiſe, as good and well meaning
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115207:13"/>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi> found by wofull experience, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. 6. The
action it ſelfe was good, his ayme and end good, and
the man (ſurely) a good man, yet he died by the immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate
hand of God, for touching of the Arke to ſave it
when the Oxen ſhook it, and it was in danger to be
broken into pieces, becauſe he had no warrant to touch
it, being not a <hi>Le vite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2 Love to God muſt be ſhewed in obeying his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands,
<hi>Joh. 14. 15, 21. 1 Joh.</hi> 2. 3, 4. and 5, 3. But the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation
of this feſtivall in honour of <hi>Chriſt</hi> (I thinke)
hath been clearly proved to be unwarrantable, not of
<hi>Chriſt</hi>'s appointment, of meer humane inſtitution, and
therefore no duty to Chriſt, It hath alſo been extreamly
abuſed to ſuperſtition and prophaneſſe, and is not on the
day Chriſt was borne, and againſt the command of the
Magiſtrate, and therefore is ſinfull, offenſive to God and
men, at leaſt to the moſt godly and judicious knowing
Chriſtians, ſinfull and dangerous to the ſoul, and if thou
be convinced that what I have here ſaid is true, then thy
obſervation of it is a ſin againſt conſcience, a preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
ſin, and ſo a dangerous ſin, which, as <hi>David,</hi> ſo all
good men ſhould carefully watch and pray againſt,
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob. But the poor complain,</hi> ſaying: This doth put down
all good houſe keeping and hoſpitality. Many Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
hereby take occaſion to lay aſide all charity, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
the poor formerly had much relief at their tables and
doors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The more is their ſin and ſhame, who make that
the occaſion to withdraw more than is meet, and a cloak
for their covetouſneſſe, I here ſpeak not againſt charity,
but againſt the unwarrantable obſervation of this feſtivall
and the ſuperſtition, great abuſes and diſorders and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſſe
of the time. <hi>Rich men</hi> may now with much leſſe
charge and trouble, be much more beneficiall to the poor,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115207:14"/>
if they pleaſe, and ought to be free-hearted and free-han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
to the poor, and to their neighbours. And I earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
intreat them in the fear of God to conſider theſe Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures
which are exceeding full of preſſing arguments to
encourage them to charity. <hi>Pro. 11. 25. The liberall ſoul
ſhall be made fat. Pro. 21. 13. whoſo ſtoppeth his ears at the
cry of the poor,</hi> (their knowing cryes, vvants and neceſſities,
though themſelves out of ſhamefac'tneſſe do not cry, <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
ſhall cry and not be heard. 2 Cor. 9. 6. He that ſoweth ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly,
ſhall reap ſharingly, but he that ſoweth bountifully ſhall
reap bountifully.</hi> As full or more full are theſe follovving,
<hi>Eccleſ. 11. 2. Pro.</hi> 11. 24, 25. and 21. 15, 26, and 22. 9. and
25. 21. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 42, 43, and 19. 21. <hi>Luke 6. 38. Gal. 6. 7, 8, 9,
10. 1 Tim. 6. 17, 18. Jam.</hi> 5. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But then <hi>Servants</hi> and <hi>Touth</hi> ſhall have no time of
liberty to refreſh themſelves; viſit their friends, and mend
their apparell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1 The <hi>Sabbath</hi> or <hi>Lords day</hi> is a day of reſt from ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile
labour appointed by the Lord himſelf, yet may not be
ſpent any part of it in carnall delights, but wholly in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
exerciſes. 2 Other time I read of none in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.
3 I am vvell contented, there ſhould be ſometime
allowed by the <hi>State</hi> for that end, and if not, ſure I am,
Maſters and Governours of families ought to allow ſome
convenient time to their ſervants for ſuch occaſions, and
do freely do ſo my ſelf.</p>
            <p>Upon the fore-mentioned grounds, and ſuch like, the
<hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Aſſembly</hi> of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed
and taken away the obſervation of December 25,
and all other holy days forbidden us to obſerve. <hi>And</hi> I
hope no truly conſcientious Chriſtian well weighing the
premiſſes, will any more plead for the obſervation of that,
or any of thoſe Paganiſh, or Popiſh holy days, nor ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
them, but rather ſtudy to honour Jeſus Chriſt by
ſanctifying his Sabboth, ſincere obedience to his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115207:14"/>
living ſoberly, righteouſly and godly in this
preſent world, and labour to abound in all works of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity:
Howſoever, I have diſcharged my duty, and the
<hi>Lord</hi> make his bleſſing go along vvith his truth.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed by <hi>R. L.</hi> for <hi>Richard Wodenothe,</hi> and are to be ſold
at his ſhop at <hi>Peters</hi> Church in Cornhill, 1651.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
